So today's דף daf is ס"ז samech zayin but we're behind, so
we pick up with the last line of ס"ו עמוד א', samech
vav amud aleph, the משנה. mishna. And we're dealing with this husband
appointing a שליח, shaliach, different languages he uses, when when he says
כתבו kitvu we assume that it means תנו, tnu,
what if you don't exactly see him, and so on. Okay, so
now the next משנה mishna is going to turn to this issue
about whether it has to be the people he appointed directly or
whether they can then hand over that responsibility to someone else. אמר
לשניים תנו גט לאשתי. amar lishnayim tnu get l'ishti. He says to
two people, give a גט get to my wife. So תנו, tnu,
you can't give it unless you write it, so obviously that includes
writing a
גט. get. או לשלושה, o lishlosha, or he says to three people,
כתבו גט ותנו לאשתי, kisvu get utnu l'ishti, write a גט get
and give it to my wife. הרי אלו יכתבו ויתנו, harei elu
yichtevu veyitnu, then it has to be they themselves who are doing
who are doing it. Okay, now, אמר לשלושה, amar lishlosha, but here's
the exception and here we see why the משנה mishna divided the
case of
כתבו kisvu from תנו, tnu, excuse me, from כתבו ותנו, kisvu utnu,
because
אמר לשלושה תנו גט לאשתי, amar lishlosha tnu get l'ishti, if he
says to three, give a גט get to my wife, so without
the כתבו, kitvu, the thinking is, or the assumption is that without
the כתבו, kitvu, תנו tnu means to some degree take the responsibility
to see that it is given, or it could mean that, right?
Because you're not specifically indicating every action that needs to be done.
So therefore the assumption in the משנה mishna is, well, when it's
two nevertheless we're not going to interpret that way because two are
not of the people, they're not a body that normally delegates responsibility.
They would be the people to do it themselves. But three is
a בית דין. beis din. And a בית דין beis din could
be understood as a body that supervises things and not that necessarily
does things personally. So when you say כתבו ותנו kisvu utnu to
the three people, then you're talking then you're being very concrete about
the actions and you mean that they themselves have to do it.
Okay?
Well, presumably what it means is that, well yes, I mean we're
going to see in the גמרא Gemara or the end of the
משנה, mishna, if you don't say כולכם, kulchem, you say to a
group of people and you don't say כולכם, kulchem, it means from
among you. So two people would sign it, one person would give
it. The גמרא's Gemara's going to discuss who actually has to do
the scribing. But nevertheless it has to be done by some distribution
of the three of them. However, if you say to three תנו
tnu and you're not specifically identifying the concrete actions that need to
be done, then that's interpreted as supervise, make sure that it's being
given over the responsibility to a בית דין, beis din, and then
they can appoint someone. So אמר לשלושה תנו גט לאשתי הרי אלו
יאמרו לאחרים ויכתבו. amar lishlosha tnu get l'ishti harei elu yomru l'acherim
veyichtevu. They are able to say to other people, they don't have
to, and other people can write it. מפני שעשאן בית דין דברי
רבי מאיר. mipnei she'asan beis din, divrei Rabbi Meir. He made them
into a בית דין beis din and gave them that role because
that's according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. וזו הלכה העלה רבי חנינא
איש אונו מבית האסורים, vezo halacha he'ela Rabbi Chanina Ish Ono mibeis
ha'asurim, and this is the הלכה halacha that רבי חנינא איש אונו
Rabbi Chanina Ish Ono brought from the prison, and רש"י Rashi says
it means from in the name of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who
was being held in prison because of the edicts, the Roman edicts.
מקובל אני באומר לשלושה תנו גט לאשתי, mekubal ani b'omer lishlosha tnu
get l'ishti, I have a tradition, presumably saying this in the name
of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, that if you say to three people
give a גט get to my wife,
יאמרו לאחרים ויכתבו, yomru l'acherim veyichtevu, that they can give that over
to other people, מפני שעשאן בית דין, mipnei she'asan beis din, because
he made them into a בית דין. beis din. אמר רבי יוסי,
amar Rabbi Yose, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says, נומינו לשליח, nominu l'shaliach,
we said to the שליח, shaliach, נומינו nominu is an interesting, it
just means אמרנו amarnu but it's like an archaic version of that
word. We said to the שליח, shaliach, אף אנו מקובלין, af anu
mekubalin, yeah that's your tradition, let me tell you what my tradition
is. My tradition is שאפילו אמר לבית דין הגדול שבירושלים, she'afillu amar
l'beis din hagadol shebirushalayim,
even were you to say to the בית דין הגדול beis din
hagadol in Jerusalem, תנו
גט לאשתי, tnu get l'ishti, give a גט get to my wife,
you didn't say כתבו kisvu and obviously they're a בית דין, beis
din, it's not just any three people, they're clearly a בית דין
beis din and you wouldn't assume the justices would then start taking
out parchment and start writing themselves. Nevertheless, that's what you said. So
if they want to do it and they want to get a
גט get to your wife, you know what they have to do?
שילמדו ויכתבו ויתנו. she'yilmedu veyichtevu veyitnu.
They have to learn how to write a גט get and write
it themselves, and they don't have to, you can always appoint other
people, but if the גט get is going to be given through
this appointment, it can only be given through they themselves doing it
directly. הרי אלו יכתבו ויתנו. harei elu yichtevu veyitnu. They can always
reject it, saying you know what, because you told me to do
it I have to do it? No no meaning they can't say
alright we'll supervise it. Correct, that's his point. His point is he
rejects the earlier פסק psak of the משנה mishna and even if
it's clearly a בית דין beis din and clearly that was your
intent it seems, or we don't really care about the intent maybe,
the word you said were you should write and therefore or you
should give and that means you have to do it personally. הרי
אלו יכתבו ויתנו. harei elu yichtevu veyitnu.
Now, אמר לעשרה, amar l'asara, now switching gears, which relates to the
earlier part of the משנה mishna but it's a different point. If
you say to ten people, כתבו ותנו גט לאשתי, kisvu utnu get
l'ishti, write a גט get and give it to my wife, okay,
and since you say כתבו kisvu clearly you did not mean that
they supervise, you meant they should do it themselves. So the question
is what do you do when you say it to more than
just one person? How is that interpreted?
אחד כותב ושניים חותמין. echad kotev u'shnayim chosmin. It means among you,
you have to write and give a גט get to my wife.
wife. I don't need all of you to do it. One person
can write it, the other person can give it, okay, well two
people sign it, one person gives it. לסיפא, l'seifa, I'm sorry, כולהון
כתבו, kulhon kitvu, if he says over explicitly all of you write
a גט, get, then אחד כותב וכולם חותמין, echad koteiv v'chulam chotmin,
one writes and they all sign, and because that's now the question
is but they're not all
writing. Does now this is going to be the first question the
גמרא gemara asks which we've sort of been eliding, which is how
much does the word כתבו kitvu here mean sign and how much
does it mean actually scribe the גט get itself? Okay, but it
certainly seems from the משנה mishnah that כתבו's kitvu fundamental meaning is
signing because if as all of them have to sign and only
one of them have to write, but not necessarily because all of
them can sign, like signatures you can just add signatures, whereas I
suppose you know it's like when they write a ספר תורה, sefer
torah, you're going to fill in a little letter because you bought
a letter, I suppose multiple people could write but it's just not
practical and you don't it's not really the same type of a
phenomenon. So in that case, even if the כתבו כולהון kitvu kulhon
is means about the writing of the גט, get, not the signing
or also means the writing of the גט, get, nevertheless we're going
to interpret it that one person writes on behalf of all of
them. What we're going to say, not to ruin the surprise, but
what we're going to say in the גמרא gemara is if they
all have to be physically present. When he doesn't say כולהון, kulhon,
he just means among you, so seven people can leave and two
people can take care of it. But when he says all of
you, so for all to sign is obvious, everybody signs. All to
write means everybody is present, it's sort of like a שליח ציבור.
shaliach tzibur. You know, everybody is present and one person represents the
group and is writing it for the group. One minute לסיפא, l'seifa,
אם מת אחד מהן הרי זה גט בטל. im meit echad meihen
harei zeh get batel. If one of them dies, the גט get
is no good because I demanded, I required, thank you, that everybody
be part of the writing of the גט. get. Again what you
see here by the way that's interesting is, and we've seen this
before but it's worth pointing out, is how much the husband controls
about this process. Meaning he can actually determine, right, it's that that
this is a פסול גט pasul get because it was not done
according to exactly his wishes. You might have said, you know what,
there's only one type of גט get in the גט, get, it
has a particular text, it's signed by two witnesses, right? So you
know, you could sort of say I refuse to make somebody your
שליח shaliach to give it, but how do you מבטל mivatel the
גט? get? And again we see that the דעת da'at and the
רצון ratzon of the husband is really central to the
shaping what is the nature of the גט get itself. And if
he wants a גט get in a particular way and it's not
done in that way, then the גט get itself is בטל. batel.
Yes, you had a question? So are we saying that if more
than one person wrote the actual document it would be a valid
גט? get?
Yeah, that could be, sure. But the משנה mishnah doesn't imagine that
that's a practical thing. So we're going to interpret כולהון כתבו, kulhon
kitvu, if it's talking about the scribing the way the גמרא's gemara
going to clarify, is that everybody's present and one person writes. But
all of you sign, or to the degree that the word write
includes signing, which it does seem so in this משנה, mishnah, then
that's easy, everybody just affixes their signature. Okay. All right, so let's
take a look at the גמרא. gemara. אמר רבי ירמיה בר אבא,
amar rabbi yirmeya bar abba, שלחו מבי רב mi'bei rav לשמואל. l'shmuel.
They sent from the ישיבה yeshiva of רב rav to שמואל, shmuel,
which is just a fascinating phenomenon in itself too because I mean
why didn't they why didn't they ask this question to רב? rav?
Okay, I don't know, maybe he was on vacation, maybe he was
out sick. Anyway, or maybe I don't know, you know, maybe it
was after I don't actually know who died first, you know, whether
רב rav died before anyway it's fascinating that the because רב rav
and שמואל shmuel were contemporaries, generally assumed to be of like equal
stature. And here they're sending from the ישיבה yeshiva of רב rav
to שמואל shmuel the following question. ילמדנו רבינו, yelamdeinu rabbeinu, let our
master teach us. אמר לשניים כתבו ותנו גט לאשתי. amar l'shnayim kitvu
u'tnu get l'ishti. If you say to two people, right, and remember
two is not a בית דין beis din regardless, it has to
be they themselves. So you say to two people כתבו ותנו גט
לאשתי, kitvu u'tnu get l'ishti, ואמרו לסופר וכתב וחתמו הם מהו? v'amru
l'sofer v'chatav v'chatmu hem mahu? But they didn't write it. They had
a סופר sofer write it and they signed it. What's the הלכה?
halacha? Because basically what they are asking is, does the when they
when you say כתבו kitvu and they have to do it themselves,
does כתבו kitvu mean the writing of the גט get or does
it mean the signing of the גט? get? And especially since the
emphasis here, you know, שניים חותמין, shnayim chotmin, אמר לשניים, amar l'shnayim,
you know, כתבו גט לאשתי, kitvu get l'ishti, clearly the reason you
need two is because you need two witnesses. All right, but that's
the question. Does it also mean that the writing has to be
done by they themselves? Okay, so שלח להו, shalach l'hu, he sends
back to them, תצא והדבר צריך תלמוד. teitzei v'hadavar tzarich talmud. You
know what? She
she has to and תצא teitzei means like if she presumably if
she got remarried on the basis of this גט, get, she can't
stay with her with her second husband because it's a questionable גט
get in that case, but I need to look into it more.
I'm not sure that it's not good, but it's a ספק גט
safek get in that case, okay, whether they only if they didn't
do the actual scribing themselves. So מאי הדבר צריך תלמוד? mai hadavar
tzarich talmud? What do you have to investigate? So אילימא משום דהוו
להו מילי ומספקן לן מילי אם נמסרו לשליח אי לא נמסרו לשליח.
ilima mishum d'havu lehu milei u'misafkan lan milei im nimseru l'shaliach i
lo nimseru l'shaliach. This is going to be our basic theme for
the for the remainder of the דף. daf. Are words given over
to a שליח? shaliach? What that means is a שליחות shlichus that
does not come with a physical concrete thing. For example, remember when
the husband makes a שליח shaliach to deliver גט get to his
wife, he's giving the שליח shaliach a physical גט. get. So for
that שליח, shaliach, if that שליח shaliach gets sick, you might remember
cases where the שליח shaliach got sick and he appointed
To receive a גט get for her, and that שליח shaliach gets
sick, it's not so obvious that he can, or not only not
so obvious, it's you know, it seems very questionable whether he can
appoint a שליח shaliach to take his place because he only has
a verbal sort of you know appointment and there's not and therefore
he might not be in a position to pass that over. For
you to be represent the woman, you know, you need to hear
it directly from the woman. From me who I'm only her agent,
from me I don't have that authority to pass over and to
make you an agent in her stead. If I had that physical
גט get that represents my role or whatever, then the act of
giving over the גט get sort of that's gonna create that sense
of agency. But words alone cannot necessarily be passed on, you know,
a verbal appointment cannot necessarily be passed on. So that's the question
by a woman's שליח לקבלה shaliach lekabalah making another שליח לקבלה. shaliach
lekabalah. And it's also the issue about appointing שליחים shlichim to write
a גט get before the גט get exists. Okay, so the question
is, if I tell these two people, write a גט get for
my wife, and they can't have somebody else do it in their
stead, because that's מילי, mili, it's verbal, and it's לא מימסרן לשליח,
lo mimsaran leshaliach, it's not given over for them to pass on.
Now that by the way is pretty much the presumption of the
entire משנה, mishnah, right? The entire משנה mishnah is if I said
you guys write it, then I mean like only you, and you
can't pass it on to somebody else. Okay, and so let's take
a look what how the גמרא gemara sort of frames this issue.
This is a presumption, like let's say these guys don't know how
to write and you know that, but you know. Right, so that's
gonna be where the גמרא gemara is gonna go. So let's take
a look.
So if the question whether they can have somebody else write it,
scribe it, I'll use that word to make it clear, if the
question whether they can have somebody else scribe it is whether they
can pass on their agency to someone else, their verbal agency. Now
of course that would be funny because if that was the question,
they should also be able to pass on the agency to sign
the גט, get, right? It wouldn't be as distinction between writing and
signing. But anyway, if that's your question,
ומילי לא מימסרן לשליח, umili lo mimsaran leshaliach, yes, he meant for
them to scribe it, but the question that's being asked is, can
they pass that on to someone else? והאמר שמואל, veha'amar Shmuel, but
שמואל Shmuel says, אמר רב הלכה כרבי יוסי, amar Rav halacha ke-Rabbi
Yossi, we rule like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi in our משנה. mishnah.
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi in our משנה mishnah says even the בית
דין הגדול שבירושלים, beis din hagadol shebi-Yerushalayim, right, has to do it
themselves. So רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi clearly holds as a fundamental thing,
there is no way an agency can be passed on. You know,
you- it sounds that that might have been the assumption of the
תנא קמא tanna kamma as well, but clearly that's רבי יוסי's Rabbi
Yossi position. And so he says, so שמואל Shmuel himself says we
rule like רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, דאמר מילי לא מימסרן לשליח, de'amar
mili lo mimsaran leshaliach, a verbal agency cannot be passed on even
if it's to the בית דין הגדול. beis din hagadol. And if
that's how שמואל Shmuel rules, so how could they have had somebody
else scribe it? אלא לשמואל הכי קמיבעיא ליה, ella le-Shmuel hachi kemibaya
lei, no, no, no. שמואל Shmuel knows that you cannot pass on
a verbal agency, but here's the question about having somebody else scribe
it. הכי כתובו, hachi kisvu, when he- when the husband says write
it, כתב ידן, כתב הגט, kesav yadan kesav haget. does he mean
scribe it, or does he mean- I mean, does he mean sign
it, or does he mean scribe it? Okay, so the גמרא gemara
is- so if he means scribe it, then they can't have somebody
else scribe it for them, מילי לא מימסרן לשליח. mili lo mimsaran
leshaliach. If he means sign it, then we're gonna see in a
minute, they're not taking their appointment and passing it on, then as
Michael said, if I just told you guys sign it and I
didn't say scribe it, then implicitly what I am saying is find
somebody to write the גט. get. So you're not passing on your
agency, you're essentially just communicating to a third party my appointment of
that third party. You got that? Okay, so that's gonna be the
point. All right, so כתב ידן kesav yadan, כתב הגט. kesav haget,
תפשוט ליה ממתניתין, tifshot lei mimatnisin, learn it from our משנה. mishnah.
אמר לשנים תנו גט לאשתי, amar leshnayim tenu get le'ishti, או לשלושה
כתבו ותנו גט לאשתי, o lishloshah kisvu utnu get le'ishti, הרי אלו
יכתבו ויתנו. harei elu yichtevu veyitnu. So it says that they have
to write it, so it sounds like you're appointing them to scribe
it themselves. No, הגופא קמיבעיא ליה, hagufa kemibaya lei, no, that itself
is our question. כתבו, kisvu, when it says in the משנה mishnah
that they have to write, or כתב
ידן הוא, kesav yadan hu, does it mean that they have to
sign it, או כתב הגט הוא, o kesav haget hu, does it
mean that they have to scribe it? That's what we want to
know. Our משנה mishnah talks about writing and delivering, to what degree
does that mean signing, or to what degree does that also mean
scribing? Now, so if he- what? Well,
also the real point is that the proof should have been from
the end of the משנה, mishnah, because the end of the משנה
mishnah says if you say it to ten people, it says one
of them writes it and two of them sign it. So it
sounds like- no, besides that you could have said כתבו, kisvu, but
it sounds like that somebody in that group has to be the
scribe, right? You cannot- has to be the scribe, right? So it's
not exactly clear, but anyway, that's the גמרא's gemara question. Okay, so
now the גמרא gemara still wants to understand, okay fine, but let's
say you didn't mean scribe it, how could you get somebody else
to do it, right? So the גמרא gemara says, okay,
פשיטא דכתב הגט הוא. pishita dekesav haget hu.
The גמרא gemara says, one minute, it obviously means scribe it. דתני
סיפא, detani seifa, אמר רבי יוסי, Amar Rabbi Yossi, נומינו לשליח, numinu
leshaliach, אף אנו מקובלים af anu mekubalim שאפילו אמר לבית דין הגדול
שבירושלים, she-afilu amar le-Beis Din Hagadol she-bi-Yerushalayim, תנו גט לאשתי, t'nu get
le-ishti, שילמדו ויכתבו ויחתמו. she-yilmedu ve-yichtevu ve-yachtemu. Even if it's the בית
דין הגדול, Beis Din Hagadol, they would have to learn how to
do it. So if you say it means the scribing of the
גט, get, if you said it means the scribing of the גט,
get, so שפיר, shapia, we could understand that you could be a
בית דין Beis Din and not know how to scribe a גט.
get. Okay, that's a different skill set. Know-how. Someone would know how
to do it? They know seventy languages? Well, okay, but anyway, maybe.
Anyway, at least we could make sense of it. שפיר. shapia. אלא
אי אמרת כתב ידן הוא, Ella ei amarta ksav yadan hu, if
it meant to sign it, so מי איכא בי דינא דלא ידעי
מיכתב חתימת ידיהו? mi ka beis dina d'lo yadei michtav chasimas yadaim?
How can you say, oh, they'll have to learn how to put
sign their signatures and sign it, right? It's obviously absurd that that's
not what the משנה Mishna means. So it's a pretty darn good
proof that the משנה Mishna means the actual scribing. So the גמרא
Gemara though is דוחה docha this. אין, In, yes, איכא בי דינא
חדתא, ika beis dina chadata, there could be a brand new בית
דין Beis Din that has yet to learn how to sign their
names. I don't know, they're the בית דין הגדול שבירושלים, Beis Din
Hagadol she-bi-Yerushalayim, just sworn in, a totally new בית דין הגדול שבירושלים.
Beis Din Hagadol she-bi-Yerushalayim. Actually, now there's the whole thing about Scalia
dying, I was looking up some things about like what are the
criteria about being a Supreme Court Justice, and I was reminded that
in the Constitution there are no criteria, no, you don't have to
even like know the law, you know, anybody can be a Supreme
Court, whoever the, I mean he has to go through to be
approved by the Senate or whatever, but anyway. Okay, anyway, so okay,
it's a bad answer, but we're still asking our question. Maybe it
just means sign and it doesn't mean scribe. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this, ואי סבירא לן דהאי כתובי כתב ידן
הוא, ve'is s'vira lan d'hai ksovu ksav yadan hu, one minute, but
if כתובי ksovu means sign it and it does not mean scribe
and therefore they can have somebody else scribe it, כתב הגט כשר,
ksav haget kasher, but so that they can have somebody else do
the scribing, והאמר שמואל אמר רב אמר רבי הלכה כרבי יוסי דאמר
מילי לא מימסרו לשליח. ve'ha'amar Shmuel amar Rav amar Rebbi halacha k'Rabbi
Yossi d'amar mili lo mimsru l'shaliach. How have you gotten, I've already
answered this question for you, but the גמרא Gemara is now finally
coming back and saying, how did you get around your מילי mili
problem? They're still finding another person and having that other person scribe
it. So the גמרא Gemara says אמרי amri look, אי סבירא לן
דכתובי כתב ידן הוא, is s'vira lan d'ksovu ksav yadan hu, if
what he says "write it" means sign it and they were telling
these two to sign it and not to
and not to scribe it, כתב הגט נעשה כאומר אמרו. ksav haget
na'aseh k'omer imru. It's like say, say to them to say to
others. ומודה רבי יוסי באומר אמרו. u'modei Rabbi Yossi b'omer imru. And
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi would agree by אומר omer means the בעל
ba'al says to the two people אמרו, imru, say to somebody else
that this is what they should do. All right, which means that
there's two issues. One is the question of maybe for somebody to
be my שליח, shaliach, now this could be a question in שליחות
בכל התורה כולה, shlichus b'chol HaTorah kulo, but it's particularly an issue
by גט get with this strong emphasis of לשמה lishmah and the
בעל ba'al and the בעל's ba'al דעת da'as controlling it, which I
mentioned before. So let's at least raise this question by גט, get,
although what's the הלכה halacha in general שליחות shlichus is a separate
level of a question is a separate question, but at least by
a גט get you could say for somebody to be my שליח
shaliach in the writing or the signing or the giving, then they
have to hear it directly from me. Okay, and therefore that sort
of sense of creating that direct connection which מילי mili is necessary.
Maybe you could make a distinction. Maybe that's necessary for the writing
because the פסוק pasuk says וכתב לה ספר כריתת. ve'chasav lah sefer
krisus.
So maybe for the for it to be like my writing, maybe
has to hear it directly from me. Maybe other things, signing maybe
less so. Okay, who knows, but that's one idea which is for
him to really represent me and to be a real appointment he
has to hear it directly from me. That would be a position
that אומר אמרו omer imru is no good. I can't even say
to Michael, Michael, you know, go tell Jenna to write the גט
get for me, okay? Because even though effectively I am really appointing
Jenna not in her presence, right? I mean I then and Michael
is just sort of just informing her, but that wouldn't be good
because for her to be my scribe she has to hear it
directly from me. That's a position that אומר אמרו omer imru is
no good. But you could easily understand no, no, that's okay, I
appointed Jenna, Michael's just telling her, okay. But the other, but the
next level is I'm saying to Michael, Michael you write the גט
get for me, and Michael's saying, you know, I really don't have
time, I'm going to ask Jenna to do it for me. Then
that's a much bigger question. I didn't appoint Jenna. Does he have
the authority to appoint her to represent to take over his שליחות?
shlichus? That's whether מילי מימסרו לשליח. mili mimsru l'shaliach. So what the
גמרא Gemara says is a very reasonable sort of split פסק psak
on this, which is שמואל Shmuel can hold מילי לא מימסרו לשליח.
mili lo mimsru l'shaliach. If I appointed you, you've got to do
it yourself. You do not have the authority to pass it on.
Again, if it's a physical גט get that might the גט get
might represent your authority and maybe that could be passed on, but
in this case it's just words, you don't have that authority. But
אומר אמרו omer imru is okay. If I am telling you to
inform someone, they don't have to hear it directly from me. So
if כתובי ksovu means sign it, I tell the two people sign
the גט, get, okay, what I'm implicitly saying is find someone to
write it. That person you're going to find to write it will
be my שליח. shaliach. You'll inform that person, but you're being told
now אומר אמרו, omer imru, you're being told to find that person,
that would be good. Okay, so that is the question. When you
say to two write a גט, get, does it mean sign it
and they can find someone to write it, or does it mean,
you know, write it and they have to write it themselves? Yes.
What? You're talking about writing, we're not talking about delivering. The delivering
they would have to do because I said כתבו ותנו. kitvu utnu.
So they would have to do. Yeah, I said כתבו ותנו. kitvu
utnu. The only thing is that the only question is what's the
scope of the word כתבו, kitvu, okay? Right. That's the question. So
let's take a look now as we continue. Doesn't ותנו utnu mean
make sure it gets delivered to her either if you appoint two
other people to do it? Well, we might say it in a
case of three people and so on when you just said תנו,
tnu, okay, but right, but normally we wouldn't. Correct. So why are
we not saying the same thing? Because the word כתבו kitvu could
have a scope to mean חתמו. chasmu. And then I haven't appointed
you to write. If כתבו kitvu means חתמו... chasmu... I understand. All
right, so that's the question. But on the other hand we have
you saying to two people, right? It was really about writing and
I, you know, anyways, that's the question. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this: Okay, ומי
מודה רבי יוסי באומר אמרו umi modeh Rabbi Yose b'omer imru does
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose really agree that אומר אמרו omer imru is
okay? והתנן vehatnan we taught in the משנה: Mishnah: כתב סופר ועד.
ksav sofer v'ed. If you have something that only has an עד
אחד, ed echad, but it has the handwriting of the סופר. sofer.
So does the fact... oh, it has the handwriting of the סופר.
sofer. I know, so the סופר sofer isn't the עד. ed. You
have a different person who's the עד, ed, okay, maybe it means
and the question is, can you say the סופר sofer implicitly is
an עד? ed? Because his actual writing of the גט get is
implicitly testifying to what's being written down. Is that good? כשר, kasher,
that's כשר. kasher. That's one version of the משנה. Mishnah. ואמר רבי
ירמיה v'amar Rabbi Yirmiya but רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiya says: חתם סופר
שנינו. chasam sofer shaninu. By the way, this is you know, you
know the חתם סופר Chasam Sofer and you know what his son
called his ספר? sefer? The כתב סופר. Ksav Sofer. So it's basically
from this גמרא. Gemara. Yeah, sure, of course. חתם סופר Chasam Sofer
and כתב סופר. Ksav Sofer. So anyway, חתם סופר שנינו. chasam sofer
shaninu. No, no, no, it's not the handwriting of the סופר sofer
would not be good. The question is, the סופר sofer was one
of the עדים edim plus another עד. ed. That's what the משנה
Mishnah is saying. That's כשר. kasher. Okay, that doesn't seem like a
חידוש chiddush at all.
Okay. ואמר רב חסדא: v'amar Rav Chisda: מתניתין מני רבי יוסי היא
matnisin mani Rabbi Yose hi and our משנה Mishnah over there is
going like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose that says מילי לא מימסרן לשליח.
mili lo mimsaran l'shliach. Now we're going to... no, we're going to
see why. We're going to see how that's at all relevant, okay?
So the גמרא's Gemara going to spell it out. Okay, so let's
keep on reading the גמרא. Gemara. ואי סלקא דעתך מודה רבי יוסי
באומר אמרו v'ei salka dachas modeh Rabbi Yose b'omer imru now if
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose would agree that אומר אמרו omer imru would
be okay to inform somebody as you know that I've appointed them,
so נפקא מינה חורבא nafka mina churba a destruction will come out
of it. It'll be terrible. What will be terrible? So דזימנין דאמר
להו לשנים d'zimnin d'amar lehu lishnayim I'll say to two people, אמרו
לסופר ויכתוב ולפלוני ופלוני ויחתמו. imru l'sofer veyichtov uleploni uleploni veyichsomu. I'll
say to them: go tell the סופר, sofer, that's אומר אמרו, omer
imru, right? Go tell the סופר sofer to write it and tell
פלוני Ploni and פלוני Ploni to sign it. ומשום כיסופא דסופר umishum
kisufa d'sofer
but now these people that I made these messengers to inform the
proper people, because I'm allowed to make them messengers to inform people,
right? Because אומר אמרו's omer imru okay. Everybody with me? So if
אומר אמרו's omer imru okay, I've appointed somebody, Michael, to go find
a סופר, sofer, find get so-and-so as a סופר sofer and get
ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon as the witnesses. Now Michael says, the
סופר's sofer going to be offended. He's going to say, 'What? You
had to get two other witnesses? I'm good enough to write the
גט, get, I'm not good enough to sign? You don't think I'm
a כשר kasher עד?' ed? So because Michael is so concerned about
the embarrassment of the
סופר, sofer, וחתמי חד מהנך סהדי וסופר בהדיה vechasmi chad mehenach sahadei
v'sofer bahadei and he'll change my שליחות shlichus a little bit and
he'll have the סופר sofer be an עד ed and I'll get
ראובן Reuven and I'm not going to get שמעון. Shimon. Okay, whatever.
Now ובעל לא אמר הכי uva'al lo amar hachi and I didn't
say that. So the גט get is פסול, pasul, but people will
think the גט get is כשר. kasher. So basically what the גמרא
Gemara is saying is that a חתם סופר ועד, chasam sofer v'ed,
to us we can easily imagine a scenario where the סופר sofer
wasn't intended to be an עד, ed, but he was made an
עד ed because you were afraid to tell him that you know,
to get other people. The גמרא Gemara imagines that that's a likely
scenario. And therefore the גמרא Gemara says, there's no way we would
allow this גט get to be good because we'd have to be
concerned about that scenario. You know the only way we wouldn't have
to be concerned about that scenario is if the husband had to
appoint people directly? If אומר אמרו omer imru was no good and
the husband had to appoint people directly, there would be no concern
that the message would have been misrepresented. All right? So that's why
we said חתם סופר ועד chasam sofer v'ed is רבי יוסי. Rabbi
Yose. It presumed that according to רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, everybody had
to hear everything straight from the husband. And then חתם סופר chasam
sofer is not going to be a problem. But if it's a
way that I can tell somebody to tell other people, so how
do we allow חתם סופר, chasam sofer, right? That could easily be
that they got embarrassed and it wasn't what I intended. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אמר לו amar lo כיון דאמר מר כשר ולא
תעשה כן בישראל kivan d'amar mar kasher v'lo ta'aseh chen b'Yisrael since
we say yes, it is כשר kasher חתם סופר, chasam sofer, but
it is, should never do something like this. Okay, we'll see why.
Not because of this concern, there's another concern that will come out
of the that the גמרא's Gemara going to raise at the bottom
of the דף. daf. But for whatever reason we say that yes,
בדיעבד bedieved it's כשר, kasher, but you should never do this thing,
which means that if the סופר sofer is told you're going to
sign it plus one other עד, ed, then the סופר sofer should
refuse. Not only should the husband not appoint anybody, but the סופר
sofer should refuse to do that type of a thing. So once
that's true לא שכיח *lo shechiach*, we're not afraid that you know
this bad scenario will come out about it. Okay so we tried
to say that this scenario works חתם סופר Chasam Sofer *Chasam Sofer*
because they have to hear it directly from the husband, which proves
that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi *Rabbi Yose* says אומר אמרו omer imru
*omer imru* is not good. And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no,
maybe אומר אמרו omer imru *omer imru* is good and I understand
the scenario you're concerned about, but since people aren't supposed to do
this anyway and the סופר sofer *sofer* shouldn't listen in such a
scenario, so it's not such a big deal. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says one minute.
The גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says דליחוש *deleichosh* I'm not done says the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* cause here's another possibility. דילמא אמר amar להו לבי
תרי *Dilma amar lehu l'vei trei*, אמרו לסופר ויכתוב *imru l'sofer v'yichtov*,
ואתם חתומו *v'atem chatomu*. Let's say he doesn't say get Reuven and
Shimon to sign. I say to Reuven and Shimon, I directly appoint
them and I say you guys sign just find somebody else to
be the סופר sofer, *sofer*. ואזלי הנך *V'azli hanakh*, so that presumably
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes is not a לא תעשה כן בישראל
lo ta'aseh chen b'Yisrael *lo saaseh kein b'Yisrael*. We'll see later the
bottom of the דף *daf* that when I have you find get
I don't appoint anybody directly that's a לא תעשה כן בישראל lo
ta'aseh chen b'Yisrael *lo saaseh kein b'Yisrael*. But we're assuming this case
where I've appointed the עדים edim *edim* directly, okay, but just had
them find a סופר sofer *sofer*. We assume that would be okay,
okay. But that's still going to be a problem. What's the problem
going to come out of it? Okay, and we so these people
go ואזלי הנך משום כיסופא דסופר ומחתימו לסופר בהדי חד מנייהו *v'azli
hanakh mishum kisufa d'sofer u'machtimu le'sofer bahadei chad minaihu*. So they so
Shimon decides look the סופר sofer *sofer* is going to be embarrassed,
I won't sign it, let's just have the סופר sofer *sofer* be
one of the signatures. ובעל לא אמר הכי *U'baal lo amar hachi*,
and the husband didn't say that. So again if רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi. *Rabbi Yose* did not hold of אומר אמרו omer imru *omer
imru* and you had to hear everything straight from the husband, everybody
had to hear everything straight from the husband, this scenario wouldn't happen.
But if the סופר sofer *sofer* can be appointed not in his
presence, there's still a concern of this scenario. And we assume that
this is a likely scenario cause I'm appointing at least the עדים
*edim* directly. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no, הא נמי קשב
ולא תעשה הוא *ha nami kashav v'lo saaseh hu*. No, that also
you're not allowed to do לכתחילה *lechatchila* either. We're not concerned about
it. So the גמרא *Gemara* says one minute, הני למאן דאמר קשב
ולא תעשה *hani l'man de'amar kashav v'lo saaseh*. We're going to see
at the bottom of the דף *daf* that this is debated. If
I directly appoint the witnesses but ask them to find somebody who
to write it,
there's one that says I shouldn't do I'm not allowed to do
that and the סופר sofer *sofer* shouldn't listen and there's others that
say I am allowed to do that. So if I am allowed
to do that מאי איכא למימרא *mai ika l'meimra*? What can you
say? So we're back to our question. How do you allow חתם
סופר Chasam Sofer. ועד *Chasam Sofer v'ed* according
aren't we assume that that's a scenario where they may be because
of embarrassment got the סופר *sofer* to sign it wasn't what the
husband wanted? So if רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi. *Rabbi Yose* says that
everything has to be heard directly from the husband, it's not a
concern. But if רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi *Rabbi Yose* allows for אומר
אמרו omer imru *omer imru*, if רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi *Rabbi Yose*
allows for for the appointment not to be heard directly from the
husband, then we cannot understand how we allow חתם סופר ועד *Chasam
Sofer v'ed*, why we're not concerned about the scenario that we just
described. So the גמרא *Gemara* says okay, אלא *ela* you're right fine
fine. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi? תרתי אמר *Rabbi Yose tarti amar*. רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi. *Rabbi Yose* says both. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi. *Rabbi
Yose* says you can't have pass on an appointment and you can't
even inform somebody of an of an of an appointment that the
husband made. מילי לא מימסרן Milli lo mimseran. *Mili lo mimsaran* and
אומר אמרו omer imru *omer imru* is no good. And that's why
חתם סופר *Chasam Sofer* is okay. Because according to רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi *Rabbi Yose*, all the players have to have heard it directly
from the husband. Now just pause here a moment. You know why
that actually makes an enormous amount of sense? Because going back to
the משנה Mishnah *mishna*, remember, why are we pinning all of this
whole position on מילי milli *mili* on the משנה Mishnah *mishna*? Because
in the משנה Mishnah *mishna* it was רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi. *Rabbi
Yose* who said that you could tell the בית דין הגדול Beis
Din HaGadol בירושלים bi-Yerushalayim *Beis Din Hagadol b'Yerushalayim* and they would have
to do it themselves. Now in that case I think we could
all agree that implicitly that's אומר אמרו omer imru *omer imru*. Implicitly
you did not basically want them to do it themselves or need
them to do it themselves. You implicitly meant guys can you supervise
it, right? But nevertheless רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi, *Rabbi Yose* says I
don't care, they're the only ones who can do it, which is
a clear point of you they
the only people who can do the גט get. *get* are the
people who heard it straight from the husband. And even if you
gave it to the בית דין Beis Din *Beis Din*, I don't
care how much you wanted them to pass that on, they're the
only ones who heard it from you and they're the only ones
who can write it. Okay, so that's רבי Rabbi יוסי'ס *Rabbi Yose's*
position. מילי לא מימסרן mili lo mimsaran לשליח *Mili lo mimsaran l'shaliach*,
you can't pass on an appointment, but not only that אומר אמרו
omer imru *omer imru* is no good. You can't even inform somebody
that they're to do it. The only people who can do it
is the people that the husband directly appointed. That's רבי Rabbi. יוסי'ס
*Rabbi Yose's* position. Yes. Different underpinning reasons, right? You can't pass on
the word because because you don't want that stuff but אומר אמרו
omer imru *omer imru* is about distorting the message. Yeah but even
if even if no no the distorting message was a concern by
the חתם סופר *Chasam Sofer*, but the but the problem of אומר
אמרו omer imru *omer imru* is as I was saying before is
a specific issue that to be to represent the husband particularly in
נתינה *nesina* of a גט get, *get*, it has to come through
direct appointment. Okay that's why אומר אמרו omer imru *omer imru* is
no good. So even if there's no question how that's different than
than מילי milli *mili*? Because מילי mili *mili* is that I appointed
here Michael but I appointed Michael, and Michael might not be empowered
to pass on that appointment. Whereas if I appointed Jen and just
asked Michael to tell her, I have done the appointment of Jen
but it wasn't direct. I didn't and because we I was not
directly communicating that to her, she is that then that's not a
good שליחות. shlichus Okay? So אמרו אמרו Amru Imru if that's no
good means somebody can only represent the husband if they're directly appointed
by the husband. מילי means if you're the one that was given
the agency, you don't have the authority to pass it on. Alright?
So those are two conceptually different things. You got it? Are you
processing? It's a fine distinction. It is, but you certainly understand the
הפרש. hefresh. When is it that I've appointed Jenna not in her
presence? Think about it this way. Can you make a שליח שלא
בפניו? shaliach shelo befanav? אמרו אמרו Amru Imru is saying you cannot
make a שליח שלא בפניו, shaliach shelo befanav, at least by גט.
get Okay? מילי is saying you can make a שליח שלא בפניו,
shaliach shelo befanav, but if you cannot pass on the שליחות shlichut
that you were given.
Okay? So anyway so רבי יוסי Rabi Yosi, holds both and that's
why the בית דין הגדול בירושלים would have to be the ones
to write it themselves. Alright, so אלא רבי יוסי תרתי קאמר. Ela
Rabbi Yossi tartei ka'amar. ושמואל סבר לה כוותיה בחדא ופליג עליה בחדא.
U-Shmuel savar lah kevaseih be-chada u-palig aleih be-chada. But שמואל, Shmuel, he's
the one that splits the vote. שמואל Shmuel says if you're given
the agency, you can't pass it on. מילי לא מימסרן. But if
you can אמרו אמרו Amru Imru is okay. You can appoint a
שליח שלא בפניו. shaliach shelo befanav. Okay? So therefore back to שמואל's
Shmuel's question. Remember שמואל's Shmuel's question? When you said to two people
write a גט, get do you mean write or sign? So if
you meant sign, yes? If you mean sign, then what you're saying
is, you know, you can sign whoever you want to do the
writing. And that's essentially אמרו אמרו, Amru Imru, because whoever you find
I'm okay with that person. I'm appointing the person that you find
to do the writing. Okay? And that would actually be okay and
therefore that's what שמואל Shmuel wants to know. If I meant just
sign it, so they can't hand over the signing, but they could
hand but they could find somebody to scribe it because that's אמרו
אמרו. Amru Imru. And אמרו אמרו Amru Imru is okay. Alright? Everybody
good? Yes? Alright, moving on. Jonathan, you seem a little a little
stuck. I'm just looking to see the underpinnings of אמרו אמרו Amru
Imru seems to be the fear of distorting the message. No, that
is not correct. I mean, it is true that the גמרא came
up with that because of the חתם סופר issue, but that is
I would say that's a secondary issue. The primary issue is whether
you can have שליחות שלא בפניו, shlichus shelo befanav, right? To be
represent the person, yeah. I'll side bar for you. Yeah, yeah. So
try to bracket that side bar the חתם סופר. Okay, so now
the גמרא says like this: גופא, gufa, let's go back to that
statement. אמר שמואל אמר רבי הלכה כרבי יוסי דאמר מילי לא מימסרן
לשליח. Amar Shmuel amar Rabbi halacha ke-Rabbi Yossi de-amar milli lo mimseran
le-shaliach. We rule like רבי יוסי. Rabi Yosi. אמר ליה רבי שמעון
ברבי. Amar lei Rabbi Shimon be-Rabbi. So רבי שמעון ברבי Rabbi Shimon
be-Rabbi the son of רבי Rabbi, said who, right? because now שמואל
Shmuel is saying this in the name of רבי. Rabbi's So רבי
שמעון ברבי Rabbi Shimon be-Rabbi son said I don't get you're reporting
that my father פסקן pasken like רבי יוסי. Rabi Yosi. By the
way, right? if we assume that like the משנה Mishnah which was
authored right edited by רבי, like it sounds like the משנה Mishnah
the way of the משנה Mishna is is that you can pass
it on, right? you can take you know tell three people תנו
tenu and they can pass it on, right? רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi.
sort of you know you got רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, you got
this report from רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva right from prison. So that's
so it's not exactly clear which way the משנה Mishna was coming
out. So here's what רבי's son says. אמר רבי שמעון ברבי מאחר
שרבי מאיר וחנינא איש אונו
חולקים על רבי יוסי. Amar Rabbi Shimon be-Rabbi me'achar she-Rabbi Meir ve-Chanina
Ish Ono cholkim al Rabbi Yossi. Given that in this משנה Mishna,
we've learned that both רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and חנינא איש אונו
Chanina Ish Ono reporting from רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva from prison who
disagree with רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi and say that if you say
to a בית דין תנו tenu that they can then that they
can delegate that because you've basically given them the authority to delegate.
So מה ראה רבי לומר כרבי יוסי? Ma ra'ah Rabbi lomar ke-Rabbi
Yossi? Why did why are you saying that my father in what
motivated my father to פסקן pasken like רבי יוסי? Rebbe Yosi. So
אמר ליה amar lei so he said to him שתוק בני שתוק.
shtok beni shtok. Silent my son silent. ואי אתה ראית את רבי
יוסי? ve-ei attah ra'isa es Rabbi Yossi?
You've never you never saw רבי יוסי. Rebbe Yosi You weren't זוכה
zocha to have seen רבי יוסי. He had already passed on. אילו
ראיתו? ilu ra'iso? Had you ever seen him, you would realize that
נימוקו עמו, nimuko imo, that his reason is with him. So meaning
and this is a famous phrase שרבי יוסי נימוקו עמו she-Rabbi Yossi
nimuko imo which means that anything רבי יוסי said was backed by
like very strong thought out reason and there's a presumption that we
פסקן pasken like
רבי יוסי. Okay? Generally הלכה כרבי יוסי
שנימוקו עמו. halacha ke-Rabbi Yossi she-nimuko imo. דתניא De-tanya and this is
from אבות דרבי נתן. Avos de-Rabbi Nosson. איסי בן יהודה היה מונה
שבחן של חכמים. Issi ben Yehuda hayah moneh shevachan shel chachamim. So
here's a nice change of tone or of pace. רבי יוסי, איסי
בן יהודה Issi ben Yehuda would list the praise of the sages
with interesting little like descriptors of the of the sages. רבי מאיר
חכם וסופר. Rabbi Meir chacham ve-sofer. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir was a
sage who was wise and he actually happened to be a scribe,
interesting because we're talking about scribes. יהודה Yehuda רבי יהודה חכם לכשירצה.
Rabbi Yehuda chacham le-she-yirtzeh. Look at
the wonderful compliment. He was very wise when he wanted to be.
Okay? As רש"י Rashi says when he took the time to think
things through or whatever he'd be very wise. Maybe he didn't always
do it. Now in the the side it's quotes from the ערוך
Aruch that says
כשמפתח שפתיו הוא ראש המדברים. keshemefateach sefatav hu rosh hamedabrim. So I'm
wondering if he's reading ירצה, yirtze, I don't know the grammar, but
we have that in modern Hebrew, right? להרצות leharzot means to give
a lecture, right? Yes? Everyone knows that? No? להרצאה, lehartza, anybody know
modern Hebrew? I'm pretty sure it means to give a lecture, right?
So I'm wondering if the ערוך Aruch is reading that, that he
was a חכם chacham when it came to opening up the discourse.
But anyway, רש״י Rashi says it means when he would stop to
think things through, he could be very wise. רבי טרפון גדיש של
אגוזים. Rabi Tarfon gadish shel egozim. רבי טרפון Rabi Tarfon was a
pile of nuts, which means what? Which means like of walnuts or
something, means imagine you got this big pile of nuts and you
take one. What happens? They all collapse, fall down. So רבי טרפון
Rabi Tarfon you start asking him something and then he says, and
then this, and then this, and then this, and then this, and
like it all comes pouring out when whatever you ask him about.
Does that mean...
No, it's a compliment. But it just sort of means like, yeah,
I know it sounds a little funny, but it means like, you
just get him started and like everything comes flooding
out, okay? It's שבח של חכמים. shevach shel chachamim. רבי ישמעאל חנות
מיוזנת. Rabi Yishmael chanut meyuzenet. רבי ישמעאל Rabi Yishmael was a stocked
store, okay? Anything
you want, he has all the information to give you and apparently
he knows where everything is located. Okay. רבי עקיבא אוצר בלום. Rabi
Akiva otzar balum. רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva is a warehouse that is
בלום. balum. Now רש״י, Rashi, תוספות Tosafot debate exactly what the word
means, but essentially it means divided into compartments. And in אבות דרבי
נתן Avot de-Rabbi Natan it explains what this means as interesting in
terms of רבי עקיבא. Rabi Akiva. Because normally, if you would ask
me, right, to say that you're a warehouse, basically just means that
you have a lot of knowledge. Whereas like רבי עקיבא, Rabi Akiva,
we normally associate him with his creativity, right? I would have sort
of said like, there's another משנה Mishna. in פרקי אבות. Pirkei Avot.
I forget what that other משנה Mishna says about רבי עקיבא, Rabi
Akiva, but like the
image that I would naturally associate with רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva is
the מעיין המתגבר mayan hamitgaber image, all this tremendous creativity. So what
is it? That he's a storehouse. So the remainder of אבות דרבי
נתן Avot de-Rabbi Natan there clarifies it means that when he would
learn from his רבייים, rabbeim, they would teach him like when you
learn גמרא, like it would all be mixed up, מדרש הלכה, midrash
halacha, analysis, משנה, Mishnah. it would all be like he'd learn it
all together. And then he would come home and he'd sort it
all out into the right compartment. Because by the way, the מדרשי
הלכה, midreshei halacha, the ספרא, Sifra, the ספרי, Sifrei, whatever, were edited
by the students of
רבי עקיבא, Rabi Akiva, and רבי ישמעאל Rabi Yishmael has parallel ones.
So basically he took in all this information and he systematized it.
It's sort of like the רמב״ם, Rambam, to think... I mean, I'm
serious, like you think about the prodigious feat that is you take
a look at this entire corpus and you reorganize and systematize it.
So that's what רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva did. רבי יוחנן בן נורי
קופת הרוכלים. Rabi Yochanan ben Nuri kupat harochlim.
רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabi Yochanan ben Nuri was like the basket
of the merchants who would go from town to town and they'd
have all these different wares to sell. Not exactly sure how that's
different from the חנות, chanut, from the packed store. I guess it's
smaller... unique items...
Oh, that's interesting. Not just your staples. Oh, that's a nice idea.
Okay. So it had the more unusual items. I like that. Okay.
רבי אלעזר בן עזריה קופה של בשמים. Rabi Elazar ben Azarya kupah
shel besamim. He was like the spice merchant. So רש״י Rashi says
that's basically just the same idea except it's a little bit smaller,
is what רש״י Rashi said. Okay.
משנת רבי אליעזר בן יעקב קב ונקי. mishnat Rabi Eliezer ben Yaakov
kav ve-naki. The teaching of רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabi Eliezer ben
Yaakov is only a קב, kav, is a small measure, but it's
a very clean measure. Okay. So he doesn't say a lot. He
doesn't have a lot of things that he teaches, but what he
teaches is very well sort of sifted and very clean and
very pure.
So presumably the presumption might be therefore that the few things he
does say, we would go like them. ורבי יוסי נימוקו עמו. ve-Rabi
Yosi nimuko imo. רבי יוסי, his reason is with him. Which it's
funny because you don't have the reason in the משנה. And if
anything, you ask me, the more logical reason is with רבי מאיר
Rabi Meir and רבי חנינא Rabi Chanina here, who reported it from
רבי עקיבא. Rabi Akiva. יצא בעיני בירושלים תנוגת אישי, yetzei be-ayin bi-yerushalayim
tenuget ishi, the logic, I would say, would be that they can
appoint someone. But anyway, נימוקו עמו. nimuko imo. Yes... Does נימוקו nimuko
come from עמוק? amok? Because he also explains it from the root
נועם, noam, which is like law... Oh, so the law is with
him. That's a nice explanation. So it's just a way of saying
we פוסקן pasken like רבי יוסי. We don't know why, but we
פוסקן pasken like
רבי יוסי. Right. He's authoritative.
He actually said in the משנה that he had a different tradition.
Okay. נימוקו עמו. nimuko imo. רבי שמעון טוחן הרבה ומוציא קימעא. Rabi
Shimon tochen harbeh u-motzi kima. רבי שמעון Rabi Shimon grinds a lot
and only comes out with a קימעא, kima, a little. Now that
sounds like an insult, okay? But the גמרא is going to say
what it means. We're going to explain that. תנא משכח קימעא ומה
שמוציא משכח קימעא, tana mishkach kima u-mah she-motzi meshakeach kima, he only
forgets a little bit of his learning. So מוציא motzi doesn't mean
he produces a little, it means
he expels a little. He gets rid of a little. He only
forgets a little bit. ומה שמוציא אין מוציא אלא סובין u-mah she-motzi
ein motzi ela subin and the stuff that he forgets is only
chaff. anyway is the bran, is the stuff he should have forgotten.
Okay, so all right. וכן אמר רבי שמעון לתלמידיו בני, Ve'chen amar
Rebbe Shimon l'talmidav banai, and Rebbe Shimon says to his students, my
my children, שנו מידותיי, shanuhu midotai, learn my you know my my
my attributes or as Rashi says it means you that might mean
like learn how my my method, my methodology. But Rashi also says
it means like just learn my teachings, like learn what I've taught
you, שמידותיי תרומה מתרומות מידותיו של רבי עקיבא shemidotai trumah mitrumot midotav
shel Rebbe Akiva because they are the like you know the the
the best of the best of the of the of the of
the teachings or of the methods of Rebbe Akiva. Okay, so that
was a nice little break. Anyway, we pasken like רבי יוסי. Now,
do we pasken like רבי יוסי in both aspects, right? That מילי
לא מימסרן and אומר אמרו is no good? It sounds like it,
because if אומר אמרו was good, then the בית דין בירושלים Beit
Din b'Yerushalayim should be able to appoint someone else. Okay, so that
becomes a very restrictive ruling at least by a get, right? That
everything has to be heard directly from the husband if we pasken
like רבי יוסי. So now the Gemara continues.
גופא. Gufa. אמר לשניים. Amar lishnayim. Now we're going to get to
see about this לא תעשה כן בישראל lo ta'aseh chen b'Yisrael. and
what that was about. אמר לשניים אמרו לסופר ויכתוב ולפלוני פלוני ויחתמו.
Amar lishnayim imru l'sofer veyichtov u'leploni ploni veyachtimu. אמר רב הונא אמר
רב, Amar Rav Huna amar Rav, כשרה ולא תעשה כן בישראל. keshera
velo ta'aseh chen b'Yisrael. So to appoint someone to now this is
very strange because to say כשרה keshera would now sound like אומר
אמרו is okay, so maybe we're only paskening like רבי יוסי that
מילי is no good. All right, so very strange here. All right,
so you tell to two people to tell the סופר and to
so and so to write. So everything you you you assign not
in people's presence. אמר רב Amar Rav so this he says that's
good ולא תעשה כן בישראל. velo ta'aseh chen b'Yisrael. So why not?
אמר ליה עולא לרב נחמן Amar lei Ulla l'Rav Nachman and some
say רב נחמן לעולא. Rav Nachman l'Ulla. וכי מאחר דכשרה, Vechi me'acher
d'keshera, if it's kosher, אמאי לא תעשה כן בישראל, amai lo ta'aseh
chen b'Yisrael, why should you not do this? So אמר ליה, Amar
lei, חיישינן שמא תשכור עדים. chayishinan shema tiskor edim. Ah, here's the
reason. Nothing to do with any of those issues we raised before
about perverting the message. The concern is who if if you have
two witnesses and coming and saying the husband told us that you
should write a get and you should sign the get for the
wife, so maybe maybe they're lying, right? Maybe the woman hired these
witnesses to get to do this. Now that by the way explains
why you have to tell two people. Why not just tell one
person? Tell the סופר, tell the witnesses and so on. Because that
and certainly we be afraid, how could the witnesses trust that this
is what the husband actually said? But even if it's two witnesses
reporting it, we're afraid the סופר should meaning so we're not saying
the husband shouldn't say this, לא תעשה כן lo ta'aseh chen, בישראל
means the סופר and the עדים shouldn't accept the agency. I am
not going to trust, essentially it's a type of an אומר אמרו
problem, going back to you Jonathan, not not on a principal not
on a like an עיקר הדין ikar hadin that it's not valid,
but on a concern about whether I'm really getting the real information.
On principle you should not listen to this person who's appointing you
because maybe they're really not representing the husband. Okay, that's why לא
תעשה כן בישראל. Because we're afraid that she's hired witnesses. So the
Gemara says, ומי חיישינן, U'mi chayishinan, are we really afraid of this?
והתניא, Ve'hatanya, עדים החתומים על שדה מקח ועל גט אשה, edim hachatumim
al sadeh mekach v'al get ishah, if witnesses are signed on a
bill of sale or on a get, לא חשו חכמים לדבר זה.
lo chashu chachamim l'davar zeh. They were not there's no concern. I
mean then what we're going to be concerned about every get maybe
it was forged? So the Gemara says no, מעשה לא עבדי. Ma'aseh
lo avdi. No, no. People won't sign a document. They won't forge
a document and sign it. That they're not going to do. We're
not afraid that the woman will hire witnesses or that the witnesses
will go along and agree to actually forge a get. That they
won't do. But דיבורא קאמרי. dibura ka'amri. That they themselves should not
be personally implicated. They just pass on the message, right? And then
they're not directly involved in the writing and the giving of the
get. That you might find two people that are willing to get
be bribed and are willing to do that. Okay, so that's a
reasonable concern that the woman hired these people, she they're not implicating
themselves by signing the get, they're just telling somebody else to do
it. So therefore we shouldn't listen to them because maybe the husband
did not really tell them. So now the Gemara says, who he
means the last people. Right, the סופר and the witnesses should not
should not accept an appointment that's not directly from the husband. It's
an אומר אמרו problem but not for the אומר אמרו reasons. Not
because it wouldn't be binding, but because it might not be genuine.
Okay, responsibility is on the last person. Exactly, exactly. Because if the
woman has hired these witnesses, then that's going to be that's going
to be happening. Okay, so the Gemara says like this.
דיבורא קאמרי. Dibura ka'amri. אמר לשניים אמרו לסופר ויכתוב ואתם חתומו. Amar
lishnayim imru l'sofer veyichtov v'atem chatomu. How about if the witnesses say
we're going to sign, but we're just telling the סופר to write
it? So now you've just told me that there's no concern that
the woman hired these witnesses because they're saying we're told by the
husband we're prepared to put our name to it, we're going to
sign, we're only asking you to be the one to write it.
So רב חסדא אמר כשרה. Rav Chisda amar keshera. Fine, that's okay.
I'm sorry, כשרה ולא תעשה. keshera velo ta'aseh. Even that you shouldn't
do. And here the only reason is is, you know, גזירה, gezeirah,
this will lead to that. There's no real reason you shouldn't do
this, but if we allow this, then we're going to wind up
allowing the other case. So it winds up being that in practice,
if you say כשר ולא תעשה kasher velo ta'aseh by both of
these, in practice we sort of at least פסקן pasken אומר אמרו
is no good for other reasons because, or not that it's no
good, but you shouldn't follow אומר אמרו because it might not be,
it might lead to not getting the real message from the husband.
Okay, רבה בר בר חנא Rabbah bar bar Chuna אמר no, that
is כשר ותעשה. kasher veta'aseh. As long as the witnesses are signing
themselves, the סופר can go ahead and write it. רב נחמן אמר
כשר ולא תעשה, Rav Nachman amar kasher velo ta'aseh, רב ששת אמר
כשר ותעשה, Rav Sheshet amar kasher veta'aseh, רבה אמר כשר ולא תעשה,
Rabbah amar kasher velo ta'aseh, רב יוסף אמר כשר ותעשה. Rav Yosef
amar kasher veta'aseh. So everybody has a different vote on this. Okay,
ואיכא דאפכי להו ve'ika de'apchi lehu and some reversed what רבה Rabbah
and רב יוסף Rav Yosef say. Okay, although do you even remember
what רבה Rabbah and רב יוסף Rav Yosef said? I read it
so quickly. Okay anyway, so it's really fascinating. We פסקן pasken like
רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, but it sounds like we don't fully פסקן
pasken like רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. It sounds like we only פסקן
מילי לא מימסרן לשליח pasken mili lo mimsaran leshalach that we don't
because remember by the way, anyway it sounds like there when שמואל
Shmuel said הלכה כרבי יוסי halacha k'Rabbi Yosi דמילי לא מימסרן לשליח,
de'mili lo mimsaran leshalach, like שמואל Shmuel himself really split the פסק.
psak. He did not go רב יוסף Rav Yosef fully. שמואל Shmuel
said אומר אמרו is okay. And that's the end of the גמרא'ס
Gemara's well. אומר אמרו is okay, you can appoint a שליח שלא
בפניו shaliach shelo befanav and have somebody report to that person. However,
לא תעשה כן, that you shouldn't be doing that because we're afraid
that they might not really be hearing it from the husband. Okay,
so that's but technically that is okay. Yes, usually because it's the
last one that's stated in the... No, not necessarily, especially when it
comes down in pairs like this. Yeah. Okay, אמר לעשרה כתבו גט.
amar l'asarah kitvu get. Now the last part of the משנה. You
tell ten people write it. So if you didn't say כולם kulam
it means it means from among you, some of you need to
write it and give it. If you said כולם kulam it means
you all have to be involved. תנו רבנן: tanu rabbanan: אמר לעשרה
כתבו גט ותנו לאשתי, amar l'asarah kitvu get utnu l'ishti, אחד כותב
על ידי כולם. echad kotev al yedei kulam. At one person just
writes on behalf of them which basically means just one person has
to write. They don't all have to write. כולכם כתבו, kulchem kitvu,
all of you write it, אחד כותב במעמד כולם. echad kotev bema'amad
kulam. So how are you going to get everybody to write it?
So it means everybody is present and one person writes. It's sort
of like a שליח ציבור, shaliach tzibur, you know, where he's like
the whole ציבור tzibur is praying. That's the way Rav Soloveitchik explained
such a beautiful explanation. He says the difference between תפילת לחש במנין
tefillat lachash beminyan and חזרת הש"ץ chazarat hashatz is that תפילת לחש
tefillat lachash is just תפילה בציבור. tefillah betzibur. Everybody is davenning as
individuals in the presence of a ציבור. tzibur. And the repetition of
the שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei is תפילת הציבור. tefillat hatzibur. The whole
community is davenning as one unit, it's through the mouthpiece of the
שליח ציבור. shaliach tzibur. He's representing the entire unit of the congregation.
So that's why if you have everybody standing there and one person
is writing it, that's like we're all writing it. Okay, so that
satisfies all writing it. אחד כותב במעמד כולם. echad kotev bema'amad kulam.
הוליכו גט לאשתי, holichu get l'ishti, bring a get to my wife.
אחד
מוליך על ידי כולם, echad molich al yedei kulam, one brings it
for all of them meaning meaning one of you guys bring it.
כולכם הוליכו, kulchem holichu, all of you bring the get, אחד מוליך
במעמד כולם. echad molich bema'amad kulam. They all have to get on
the plane together? They all have to right? One brings it in
everyone... Now I don't know what that means. Every step of the
way they all have to be there? Can a guy take a
little bit of a break and do some sightseeing and catch up
with the group a little later on? I mean I'm serious. Like
what at what stage you know does every step have to be...
It's another question by the way that the ראשונים rishonim ask, which
is can you send a גט get in the mail? When you
make a שליח להולכה shaliach l'holachah is it really the conveying of
the גט get that's the שליחות shlichut. or really it's the end
stage, it's just the giving of the גט get. that's the שליחות.
So it doesn't matter how it physically gets to the right place.
Right? So anyway, so presumably that more means one gives it in
everybody's presence. Okay. כולם או אחד מוליך במעמד כולם. kulam o echad
molich bema'amad kulam. איבעיא להו: iba'ya lehu: now they raise a question.
מנה אותן מהו? mana otan mahu? If he says one, two, three,
four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten, give a get to my
wife. So what do we say the counting means? Does it mean
all of you? Or does it mean from among you? Okay, now
here you see by the way according to the גמרא it's not
אסור assur to count people. Okay, maybe it means you did הושיעה
את עמך. hoshia et amecha. Okay, מהו? mahu? רב הונא אמר Rav
Huna amar מנה אינו ככולם. mana eino ke'kulam. That does not count
like you said all of you. It means any of you. רב
יוחנן משום רבי אלעזר אמר דמן רומא אמר, Rav Yochanan mishum Rabbi
Elazar amar d'min Roma amar, I don't know if that's Rome, says
מנה הרי הוא ככולם. mana harei hu ke'kulam. No, when you count
them it's like you mean everybody I counted have to do it.
אמר רב פפא Amar Rav Papa ולא פליגי. velo pligi. They don't
debate. הא דמנה כולהו הא דמנה מקצתייהו. Ha de'mana kulhu ha de'mana
miktzatayhu. The difference is did you count everybody in the room or
did you only count some people in the room? אמרי לה להאי
גיסא ואמרי לה להאי גיסא. Amri lah l'hai gisa ve'amri lah l'hai
gisa. Now which way does it go? So there's a debate. Some
say if you count everybody that more means everyone do it, whereas
if you counted some it just means yeah some of you do
it, whatever. And some say the reverse. If you counted some then
you're then you're focusing on a subgroup. So if you only counted
half the people in the room it means you that I've counted
I want all of you to do it. Whereas if I count
all of them I just somehow mean from among you do it.
Hard to exactly understand the argument either way. But anyway, okay, so
whether counting means everyone or from among you could make a difference
if you counted everyone or counted some, but you could argue that
either
way. Now... If you're
singling them out, you're doing it intentionally, but do you mean from
among the five I've counted, from you five see that a גט
get, is given to my wife, or do I mean all of
you five? Right? So that's the question. And which one more would
indicate I mean everybody? Alright, so now the גמרא ends. אתי רב
יהודה בגיטין דכולכם. Ati Rav Yehuda be-Gittin de-kulchem. Now, Rav Yehuda made
a תקנה takanah that when a husband wants to say כולכם, kulchem,
that they should know that there's a particular נוסח. nusach. And he
wanted to make the נוסח nusach a way in which it would
not lead to the problems, basically to make it not mean כולכם.
kulchem. So here's the נוסח nusach you should say when you're doing
the כולכם. kulchem. כתבו או כולכם או כל חד וחד מנכון. Ktovu
o kulchem o kol chad ve-chad minchon. You guys write the גט.
I don't care if it's everyone or if it's any one of
you. חתומו שתיין או כולכם או כל תרי מנכון Chatomu shtein o
kulchem o kol trei minchon or any two of
you. אובילו או כולכם או כל חד וחד מנכון. Ovilu o kulchem
o kol chad ve-chad minchon. So have the husband explicitly say either
all or everyone, so we don't have to worry that everyone who
wasn't there. Because obviously if you say כולכם, kulchem, it's making it
much harder to do. אמר רבא לא זימנין דגייז ליה לדיבוריה, Amar
Rava lo zimnin degayiz lei lediburei, ואמר כולכם ולא אמר כל חד
וחד מנכון. ve-omar kulchem velo amar kol chad ve-chad minchon. That's not
a good way to say it. Don't say write a גט, all
of you or any one of you. Why start with the all
of you? The all of you is the problem. He'll just say
all of you and he won't finish the end of the sentence.
ואתי ליפסולי ve-ati lipsulei and it'll become פסול. pasul. אלא אמר רבא,
Ela amar Rava, here's what you say. כתבו כל חד מנכון. Ktovu
kol chad minchon. Basically, just establish a text that doesn't even acknowledge
the idea of כולכם. kulchem. Write it, any one of
you. חתומו כל תרי מנכון. Chatomu kol trei minchon. אובילו כל חד
מנכון. Ovilu kol chad minchon. So basically teach people a text that
doesn't lead to saying כולכם, kulchem, because כולכם kulchem is just asking
for trouble. Okay, הדרן עלך האומר. Hadran Alach Ha-Omer. Alright.